Then we shipped it to production and someone came to me and said,
this is wonderful, but you haven't accounted for the context length at all.
when I'm trying to set a threshold for this kernel,
I have to change it all the time because not normalized.
So then I had to go away and go, okay, well, fine.
Let's normalize by the sequence length of kV,
which is where the divide in that slide comes from.
Was basically because somebody sent me
an angry message on slack and said, this is really hard to use.
This this talk
might give us a little bit of whiplash, actually,
because I feel like we're going to go from very high level
kind of AI stuff to right,
right into the depths of attention kernels and optimization and stuff.
So it should be fun.
I will also give some credit to Claude,
probably like everybody here is going to have to do at some point.
I did take a different approach that.
So what I tend to do is write the slides myself, and then I have Claude
tell me just how terrible they are, and then then go through and fix them all.
So a quick agenda on this talk really.
So this is all about what I refer to as long context inference.
And it's not an optimization exercise
for the attention kernel in Cuda.
Some benchmark results and a kind of takeaways really.
So I talk about long context.
So what do I mean by long context.
And why is it important.
So not so long ago really kind of like an 8000 token context window.
It was considered a really big deal.
And today now like frontier models like like Claude Opus, they ship with,
you know, context windows up to a million, million tokens.
So that shift isn't really just a number either.
It kind of changes what you can do with the model.
I know certainly for me as a developer, the way I work now is totally different
to the way I worked probably 18 months, two years ago.
Just very rapid pace of change.
So some of the kind of things we can do now are listed on this slide.
So more complicated system prompts document analysis.
One of my favorite uses is probably is summarizing those horrendously long email
chains that I come into in the morning that I definitely do not have time to read
really large code bases.
Probably a big one for me is a as a dev tech, I work on all three
of the inference libraries, so SG lang VLM, tree Elm.
I've probably touched all of those in the last 3 or 4 months,
and every time I come back to one of them, it looks completely different.
So usually the first thing I do
is ask core to tell me what's changed and how do I find what I'm looking for
and kind of attention.
Costs, like the cost of the attention kernel, scales linearly
with like sequence length per token, which means it's quadratic, really.
And kind of every new token generated has to attend to the previous context
and at 1 million context, basically that gets really expensive.
And this is what this talk is about, kind of addressing in a way.
So anybody who's super familiar with the math behind attention
is probably going to be really bored by this slide,
but I didn't want to assume that everybody would know exactly how it works,
because if you don't kind of
have an idea of this diagram, you don't really understand the optimization.
So kind of the intuition
is obviously the every token that the model is processing.
Attention is basically asking which of the other tokens in this sequence
are relevant to me, and what does that tell me?
So Q is your queries, which is the question that each token is asking.
K is kind of a label associated with each token, and v
the value is what that token contributes if it's selected.
So if you multiply q by the transpose of k,
you get what we call like a matrix of attention scores.
And this is a sequence length
by sequence length matrix of compatible compatibility.
And then you do an operation called softmax
which we're going to come to to in more detail in a second.
A key in the title of this talk, softmax is kind of important here.
And that gives you basically a probability distribution
Q times the transpose of K is a matrix multiplication, which we really like.
On GPUs we have ten scores that make those really fast.
And then softmax has this exponential.
And it's interesting because actually on some of our hardware
we're actually bottleneck by the exponential more than we are
by the matrix multiply
kind of
on the right here we have what we call multi-headed attention,
which is this attention process applied to multiple heads in parallel.
Yeah.
So now a little bit about softmax.
I've just said that softmax is really important.
And the algorithm here like online softmax
came up with the by guy I've cited on this slide, Maxim Malakhov.
He's in my team. He's super smart.
And I think he probably gets some personal satisfaction
every time I mention his paper at one of these talks.
So the problem with naive
softmax is basically that you need a global max across all of the keys.
And that means in order to keep your numerical stability
so that you don't overflow.
The problem is you don't know the max until you've already processed
all the elements, which means you need at least two passes.
And over this big matrix.
I think it's really expensive.
So thanks to Maxim, we have this online softmax which allows you to process this
in a single pass.
And the idea is basically you have to keep a running max and do some checking.
That means you can do a correction at the end.
Now this running max really is a super important
because we use it to check whether we can skip the softmax later.
So we should really pay attention to that.
So there's kind of three properties to keep in mind.
Single pass.
Which means we don't have to materialize the full attention matrix in memory
in any one time.
This is kind of one of the key optimizations behind flash attention.
It's like reading that matrix over and over again is really expensive.
Numerically stable is super important as well.
So naive
softmax requires two passes, three operations per tensor element.
Safe softmax subtracts the max to eliminate the overflow,
but that also requires
that requires three passes and four memory operations per element.
Online reduces this back to three.
So we talked about attention being expensive.
The really interesting part about attention is that despite
being super expensive, it's actually also very sparse.
So this kind of diagram on the slide here is showing you
basically the result of queue times k.
And these kind of squares that are highlighted in
gray are the ones that are like I don't know really what to say.
It's kind of like an informal term but important.
So it's kind of weird is that we do all of this work,
and yet a lot of it doesn't really contribute to the result.
So oftentimes attention I think I've cited on the slide here.
In some cases it can be up to 96% of your workload.
So the idea that I'm saying that a lot of this work is actually wasted
is kind of really not ideal, right.
So this is taking a changing of tack a little bit.
So the kernel I'm trying to say this,
this presentation is basically an exercise in kernel optimization.
And the kernel that I worked on is a kernel from Nvidia
that we called FMA, which is a fuzed multi-headed attention.
It's a bit like flash attention, except I think we support a bit more.
I think a lot of the key optimizations are the same.
And it turns out that actually in order to write a good attention
kernel, you can't really do that in one kernel.
You need like hundreds of attention.
Kernels are optimized for different scenarios.
So for your context kernel versus your generation
phase kernel require a very different optimizations.
Because when you're doing generation you only generate one token
and then you're attending to the entire previous cave cache.
And that changes the shape of your matrix multiply.
So basically
what we decided to do was we wrote a code generator called TR.
And basically we use that to
help us maintain all of these kernels because we realized it would be easier
to write one generator and then generate the kernel we need,
versus have me maintain potentially thousands of attention kernels.
I think currently off the top of my head inside tensor RT Elm on GitHub,
I think we have 4000 kernel binaries for attention,
and that often blows up even more when somebody like me comes along
and says, hey, can we get a skips off max variant of all of these, please?
And then you multiply it by two.
The kernel is warp specialized for anybody who doesn't know what that means.
A warp is basically a group of 32 threads that operate in parallel on GPU.
And when we say warp specialized, we mean each warp gets a different job to do.
And this is kind of a method to allow us to keep all the different execution
units on the GPU busy.
So memory may your softmax unit, not softmax unit
and multifunction unit, which you used to calculate softmax.
So for example, in attention, in flash attention, often what happens
is we use one warp to load tiles of the matrices, another warp.
What we do in matrix multiplies.
Somebody else will be doing softmax, and then somebody else
is writing out the output.
And kind of synchronizing all of these very different stages of the pipeline
is super hard to do by hand, which also kind of lends itself to a code generation
kind of method just because it's so much to holding your head
as a programmer, I don't necessarily think it's feasible to do by yourself.
So there are more
tasks in the kernel than listed on this slide.
But basically when I say a task,
I mean, this is something we're getting a specialized warp to do.
And the key ones that we care about are kind of listed in this table.
So like the load task does.
Well, it's kind of in the name really.
It loads data from global memory.
And this is basically for reading QQ and V we have the main task
which issues instructions to the tensor cores softmax task.
And that reads the result of what we call BM one which means
batch to matrix multiply and BM one refers to q times k.
So if I say bm one, that's what I mean.
If I say two, it's the p times v matrix multiply.
And we finally have the correction task which is relevant to
Maxim's online softmax.
So it's kind of.
Get an idea of why this works or what this optimization is going to be.
And I promise this is the only maths we're going to do together
in this presentation.
I said before that a lot of the attention values that we are
calculating are end up being zero after softmax or close to zero.
So that means then when you do your p times v bm two,
that's something interesting happens.
Say you have a row of this matrix that is all zeros.
What does that mean for your result.
Well it turns out that that also means
that the result of that matrix multiply for that row is also zero.
So what if I told you we could just, you know, not bother doing it?
Because what's the point.
It's not changing the answer anyway.
So I think anybody who's familiar with flash
attention would have seen a diagram like this before.
Basically, to avoid realizing
the full attention matrix in memory, we break it up into tiles.
That's kind of shown
in this diagram here, where you do one q times k for a given tile,
and then you softmax that tile, multiply it by v and accumulate it into the output.
So that's kind of the loop.
It makes it very memory efficient.
What it doesn't do, however, is work out whether that attention calculation
is actually worth doing, which is kind of what I keep coming back to.
So many of these tiles are producing softmax values that are essentially zero
or close to zero.
And something, something that we'll come back to you
later is the idea that you can tune how aggressive this skip is,
but that obviously has trade offs in terms of accuracy and performance.
So this isn't a corner case either.
Like I said before, attention is sparse.
If we go back to that vertical slash diagram from before, most of those are
squares were white not gray.
So essentially we have a really complicated kernel that processes
loads of tiles, but a workload where most of those tiles don't actually matter.
And we call this kind of skip softmax.
It turns out, actually, that we're skipping a lot more than the softmax.
And oftentimes
softmax is not actually the most expensive operation that we're skipping.
But, well, we've named it now. So
so the key insight here is how can we skip the tiles
cheaply using information that we've already calculated.
We have this running max that we're keeping for softmax for online softmax.
And that's that's a result of q times k which we've already done.
So kind of calculating this value is not additional work.
So when a new tile arrives we do this batch matrix multiply.
And you take a row wise maximum of each tile that's a local max.
And you compare that to the running max.
Now this is cheap because we were doing this reduction anyway.
Anyway we see in this kind of equation here, the key is
if your local max is much less than your running max,
and by much less I mean the difference would be a large negative number.
Then the result of the exponential is basically zero.
Now that means
if all of the softmax values for that tile would be near zero,
that entire tile contributes nothing to the output.
So we can just set them to zero and not do a bunch of extra work.
So if you kind of look at this diagram here,
you're asking yourself this question have we triggered this threshold or not?
If we haven't triggered it then we're very sad and we have to do all this work.
And if we do trigger it, we can skip the exponential, the normalization
loading of the v tile, a matrix multiply, and the correction step.
And the kind of really nice thing about this
is that you don't need to do any additional training on your models.
It's just an inference time thing.
You can just deploy it and use it
so you save in various ways really.
And that's kind of what this slide is trying to say.
You may hear like a kernel developer
talk about a kernel being compute bound versus memory bound.
When we say that if you're compute bound, it means you spend most much of your time
doing math. And that's kind of your bottleneck.
Whereas if you're memory bound,
you're kind of bottlenecked by, well, the memory subsystem.
Now, if we kind of walk through this, basically
what I've got is a diagram here that shows you all the different parts.
I've just said we're skipping and what exactly you save from skipping them.
So when you skip the softmax and the normalization, that's a compute saving.
You also have to keep statistics to do your correction.
That's also a compute saving.
The really interesting one is the V tile because that's the only memory
saving here.
And in fact for some some versions of this kernel, we don't actually skip this
because if it's a compute bound kernel you're not bottlenecked by that load.
So delaying the war but then has to decide whether to skip
or not actually hurts you more because it doesn't buy you anything.
In a non memory bound situation,
P times V saves you tensor cores, which obviously we care about.
And then the correction we've kind of already talked about.
Interestingly skipping the correction is an optimization that already existed.
We did it prior and I think flash attention does it as well.
But it turns out if you're skipping softmax
you can also combine it with this other optimization.
So kind of the skip condition like how does it work?
I said before, a warp is basically a group of 32 threads.
So each thread needs to decide whether to individually skip,
because the way we kind of write this kernel or the version
of the kernel that I care about, each thread basically has a row of the tile.
When you're doing this softmax calculation, and you do this exponential
that is effectively measuring how much smaller is this tile
maximum versus the running global max.
And this threshold is is user tunable.
It turns out actually that picking a good value for the threshold is really hard.
When I was
when I was developing the kernel, I didn't really fully appreciate that.
Right?
I would just set a value for my unit test to check it against a reference
and then go, great.
Then we shipped it to production and someone came to me and said, this
is wonderful, but you haven't accounted for the context length at all.
So it turns out that when when I'm trying to set a threshold for this kernel,
I have to change it all the time because it's not normalized.
So then I had to go away and go, okay, well, fine.
Let's normalize by the sequence length of kV,
which is where the divide in that slide comes from.
Was basically because somebody sent me
an angry message on slack and said, this is really hard to use.
So after
that, basically what you need is all of the threads
or all of the warps that are processing a tile need to agree.
So to do that within a warp we have this handy intrinsic called all sync,
which is really fast, but it turns out to do softmax effectively.
You need four warps and multiple warps.
Can't talk to each other, so you have to do some atomics
and shared memory, which is a bit slower, but that's just the way it is.
So I've probably spent now close to 15 minutes
telling you all about this kernel and how it works.
And really the question that everybody probably has is, well,
this is all well and good, but does it actually work in practice?
So the does it work?
Part of the presentation is basically the next few slides.
And I'm going to frame it essentially a specific questions that we need to answer.
These questions being well what's the overhead when we don't skip.
And how fast is it for context or pre-filled kernels,
and how fast is it for generational what we call decode kernels?
And even if your attention kernel is faster,
does this actually show up end to end when you run a model?
Because if your bottleneck is something else,
you can make attention as fast as you want.
It doesn't really doesn't really help you in any way.
So this kind of graph shows overhead analysis
and basically what we're kind of seeing, or what
I saw when I profiled this is certainly
a lot of the time that the overhead is basically a function of profiling noise.
And it's actually really hard to capture. This is not so much
the case for generation kernels where it's a bit slower.
What this graph is showing is basically
one is no overhead and then lower than that is slower.
But for generation case we're still actively optimizing this.
It turns out
the memory bound case is really hard because the matrices are really small.
So there are two kernels or two types of kernels we really care about.
Context is when you do your pre-filled.
So this is before you've got your cave cache.
And when you generate your KB cash for this, I, I will
I focus mostly on BFF 16 and PHP.
And what this is, is I'm on the x axis.
We have what we call sparsity.
And sparsity is effectively what percentage of the attention tiles
have we skipped.
So 100% is we did no work and 0% is we didn't skip at all.
You can never skip the first tile.
Otherwise the threshold check doesn't work.
And I suspect that if you skip all of the tiles, everything
probably collapses into garbage anyway.
So I think the extremes are either end of this graph are not particularly useful.
What we care about probably is this this area in the middle.
Speedups are lower than what we got for BFF 16.
And that's kind of a consistent theme throughout this talk.
And we're still kind of investigating that
generation is a very different kernel to to a pre fill.
It turns out basically because you're attending to the entire kV cache,
but you're only receiving or processing one new token.
Your Q matrix is really skinny.
And the work then becomes
dominated by loading k and v instead of your matrix multiply.
This kind of
brings us back to the cascade like savings diagram I had before.
Stage three is basically when you skip a tile,
the V tile is not loaded and kind of in the context kernels most of the time.
I think I mentioned before,
we just don't bother doing this because the extra extra weighting is not worth it.
But on a generation kernels like this, if you don't do the
the load skip, you get no benefit at all.
I think partly as well.
Why fate benefits, at least less in this case is I think we're just moving
less data, but that's a bit more clear to me than the pre-filled case.
Finally, end to end testing.
I didn't run these tests,
but I think an esteemed colleague of mine tested, I think it was Queen
three on two benchmarks that I called Long Bench V1 and Long Bench V2.
I think it would have been negligent of us
to not use a long context kernel to test this.
So for long bench v1
versus b2 v2 for v2, we could only fit a batch size of one.
Just because the context is so long,
you end up in the GPU if you try to run multiple prompts.
The speed up shown in this graph is based on time to first token.
We're still working on the time
per output case, and I think what's really interesting
is that you can actually get a large amount of the speedup
shown in this graph without taking too much of hits your accuracy.
The problem is,
is that because this is model dependent,
it means whoever's deploying that has to spend a load of time
calibrating it to try and work out what their acceptable threshold
is, though maybe, maybe now you just get clawed to do it.
So where can you use this?
So right now it's in Tensor Realm and in a library
I think that Nvidia maintains called flash info.
It used to be.
I think it was the result of a PhD project, but somehow we ended up
taking it over.
But we flash infer has basically become
the library that we open source all of our kernels through
and through flashing for this is available in SG lang as well.
It's going to be available in VLM.
I happen to work with the guy who's adding it.
I think he's like halfway through.
There are some PR numbers on this slide if he's interested,
and there is some code snippets here.
And what's kind of nice about this,
we don't really need to walk through them in detail.
What's kind of nice basically, is that to use this,
the only thing you need to specify is this threshold.
Your API doesn't really change.
There's no like hairy kind of change to all of your scripts or anything.
You can just set a value and kind of go, you just need to spend
some time deciding whether you're happy with the results or not.
So what are the key takeaways.
So doing this like skip softmax
eliminates loads of redundant compute and memory traffic.
The threshold is designed to basically be a really clean knob that you can tune.
It's kind of easy.
I've got I think I have scripts at home that are just loops over this threshold
measuring different performance things.
That's how we kind of got most of the graphs in this presentation.
And it's most impactful for long context workloads.
So for the ones we mentioned at the start for future work,
I'm kind of interested in what could we do like an adaptive threshold
or could we potentially set different thresholds per layer?
I think somebody tried that, but it turned out getting the correct
threshold is really hard, but maybe we just need to look a bit deeper.
I'd also be curious to see if we could combine it
with some of the existing smart attention techniques,
whether we could benefit in multiple ways at once.
There are some links on this slide.
I think we have a paper and various blogs I appreciate.
You can't really click them while it's on this projector.
Yeah, I think that's my last slide.
Make me for the cube are you know.
You got some questions are excellent.
Oh sorry.
You can't ask you a question.
No you didn't catch it.
Thanks for the door.
That was super interesting.
Can you use this during model training?
And if you did. That's a great question.
I think I'm an inference person, so I'm not the best person to ask about that.
I think in the paper that I've linked there,
there is a mention to training, so it might be worth having a read.
I can also probably speak
to some of the training people at work and get back to you.
Get back to you.
So if you want to talk to me during the networking,
we can exchange details and find out.
Thanks again.
A lot of that went above my head,
but I noticed in one of your parameters you use instruct model.
So is this what you're trying to do restricted to?
I think it shouldn't be, but is it a secret to model types or model category?
No, I think. You use it on all flavors of models.
You can.
It's basically a drop in replacement for attention.
I see no reason why you couldn't use it for anything else.
You'd obviously have to do your own testing on whether you'd be happy
with the results or not, but there is nothing.
I guess what you're actually asking me is, is there some constraint in the kernel
that means this wouldn't work with a non instruct model?
And to my knowledge, the answer is no.
It should be fine. Cool. Thank you.
Any other questions?
They're making you work really hard.
Tom. Really worried behind.
The camera.
You said you used.
To code while.
Yes. Because honestly, because the day I wrote this presentation
was the first day I got a Claude coworker license, and I decided to try it out.
What's the.
What's the mic?
I feel like every time I go to work, we've got access to another
AI tool that's amazing.
At another Thing and my, my toolbox of like my toolbox of AI tools to use
at work is so large, I always struggle to pick the correct one.
If no one's.
There's one.
Since you got a whole suite of models
access to internally and externally, have you tried to benchmark
across a whole bunch of these models, and
do you have like a result set somewhere that you can do that?
There may be a spreadsheet internally I would need to check.
Certainly when we were developing this, we had we had interest from clients.
I think there was a few times I got an email from some people,
some someone's asking me about skip softmax.
Is it really?
I think a lot of the SG lang community were interested in it,
which is probably why that PR went out so, so quickly before VLM.
But I think, yeah, there probably is some data,
but if if it exists, I haven't seen it.
Okay. Interested in that if you can.
Awesome.
Any other questions?
All good.
Please give it up for.
Some water.